<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Aarons bells a-sounding In a sermon, tending cheiftly [sic] to admonish the ministerie, of their charge, &amp; duty. Preached by M. Samuel Hieron at a general visitation neere Bristow. And now published by them to whom his coppy was entrusted after his death.</title>
            <author>Hieron, Samuel, 1576?-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03267</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13385</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116920</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852135</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852135</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17442</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03267)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17442)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1382:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Aarons bells a-sounding In a sermon, tending cheiftly [sic] to admonish the ministerie, of their charge, &amp; duty. Preached by M. Samuel Hieron at a general visitation neere Bristow. And now published by them to whom his coppy was entrusted after his death.</title>
                  <author>Hieron, Samuel, 1576?-1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 37, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Holland? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed 1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Central Library (Bristol, Eng.).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17442:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AARONS BELLS A-SOVNDING.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In A SERMON, tending cheiftly to admonish the</hi> miniſterie, <hi>of their</hi> charge, <hi>&amp;</hi> duty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Preached</hi> by M. SAMVEL HIERON at a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>viſitation</hi> neere <hi>Bristow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now published by them to whom his coppy was entruſted after his death.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mal. 2.1.</bibl>
               <p>And now <hi>ô Preiſts</hi> this Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is for you.</p>
            </q>
            <p>PRINTED. 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:17442:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17442:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was ſaid of old,<note place="margin">Ier. 23.15.</note> that from the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> was wickednes gone forth, into the whole land: And, it may be ſaid, as truly this day. that, the Sinns of the <hi>miniſters,</hi> have infected, the whole Eſtate.</p>
            <p>Now indeed, by the rule of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> it muſt needs be ſo: <hi>If the light</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>which is in thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">mat 6.23.</note> 
               <hi>be darknes, how great is that darknes?</hi> If the calling, which should give direction to others, be it ſelfe corrupted how great muſt that corruption be? If the <hi>founteine</hi> be poyſoned, all, that <hi>drinke</hi> thereof, muſt needs be in danger. I am, by the mercie, of him that hath called me, a Chriſtian: therefore, cannot but even honour, the feete of Gods <hi>meſſengers:</hi> I am a <hi>miniſter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10.15.</note> and alſo am bound, to mainteine the credit, of the calling: but let my tongue, cleave to the roofe of my mouth, rather then I shoule uſe it, to the <hi>licking</hi> over thoſe ſores, which, except they be <hi>launced</hi> to the quicke, and <hi>ſearched</hi> to the bottome, can never be cured. And wretched is that <hi>kindnes,</hi> which goeth about, to heale the hurt of the <hi>church,</hi> with ſweete words: ſaying, all is as it should be, when the <hi>garden</hi> of the Lord, lyeth, like the feild of the <hi>Sluggard,</hi> and his <hi>vineyard,</hi> like the <hi>vineyard</hi> of him that is idle: and <hi>Sion,</hi> even now,<note place="margin">Jer. 4.31.</note> as in time paſt, ſigheth, and ſtretcheth out her hands, and
<pb facs="tcp:17442:3"/>
cryeth, <hi>woe is me, my ſoule fainteth, becauſe of the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What man can ſee, the deſolation of the Lords howſe, by dumbe <hi>Idoles,</hi> incroaching <hi>Simoniacks,</hi> drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy <hi>Demaſſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">iob. 32.18</note> ubiq uitarie <hi>Non-reſidents;</hi> but his ſpirit with in him, (if he have but a dramme of zeale) will even compel him, to lift vp his voyce, and cry a lowd, againſt thoſe,<note place="margin">Eſay. 58 1</note> who have no <hi>remorſe,</hi> over their ſoules, for whome Chriſt died? The earneſt deſire, to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by all good meanes, the ſpeedy <hi>reformation,</hi> of theiſe groſſe <hi>corruptions,</hi> ſtirred vp, the worthy <hi>Authour,</hi> of this fruitfull <hi>Sermon,</hi> being called to preach at a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>viſitation</hi>) to imploy part, of that <hi>precious</hi> gift, where with the Lord, in a large meaſure, had endowed him, to that moſt neceſſarie, important purpoſe. As the <hi>text</hi> was excellent, for the thing intended: ſo hath he handled it: I <hi>ſpeake</hi> my <hi>opinion,</hi> and doubt not, but thou wilt joyne with me, when thou shalt <hi>peruſe</hi> it: except, thou art <hi>forestalled,</hi> either againſt the <hi>man,</hi> or againſt the <hi>matter:</hi> his handling of it, as may be ſeene, was ſuch, as neither <hi>wrung</hi> in ought, that might be thought impertinent; nor omitted any <hi>obſervation,</hi> which the words, kindly, and voluntarily, might not afford. The <hi>ſence,</hi> is delivered <hi>ſoundly:</hi> the <hi>diviſion</hi> made <hi>artificially,</hi> the <hi>doctrines</hi> rayſed <hi>naturally,</hi> prooved <hi>ſubstantially,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. tim 2.15.</note> and applyed powerfully; heere is <hi>art:</hi> the words cut a-right, heere is <hi>learning,</hi> the declaration of the trueth, heere is <hi>eloquence</hi> in the plaine evidence of the <hi>ſpirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2 4</note> heere is <hi>zeale</hi> allayed with <hi>mildnes</hi> of the ſpirit, and <hi>sharpnes</hi> of reproofe, tempered with ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of exhortation.</p>
            <p>Such, as thou ſeeſt his <hi>Sermon</hi> to be, were his <hi>weekely</hi> exerciſes: ſuch was his <hi>doctrine,</hi> ſuch was his <hi>life,</hi> for
<pb facs="tcp:17442:3"/>
               <hi>gravitie,</hi> admired: for amiablenes, for readines, either to admonish, or exhort, according to occaſion, for <hi>bowells</hi> of compaſſion, to the poore, even a <hi>continuall</hi> Sermon. Few ſuch <hi>Elthues,</hi> ſo full of matter: ſuch <hi>Timothes,</hi> ſo nourished vp, in the words of faith,<note place="margin">iob, 32.18. 1. tim. 4.6 Eſay. 57.2</note> and of good doctrine, which he <hi>continually</hi> followed. And as he walked, before God, in his life time: ſo now he <hi>resteth</hi> from his labours, in him: and is joyned to the <hi>company</hi> of innumerable <hi>Angels,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 14. Heb. 12.22.23. mat. 9.28. phil. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.23.24. Eſay. 57.1</note> &amp; to the <hi>ſpirits</hi> of juſt and perfect men. It was to the <hi>churches</hi> great loſſe, that in this <hi>ſcarſity,</hi> of faithfull labourers, he abode no longer in the flesh: but, as for him, it was a <hi>benefit,</hi> to be ſo ſoone <hi>diſſolved,</hi> being thereby taken from the evill to come: and gone to <hi>Christ</hi> which is beſt of all. But, I will hold thee no longer, from <hi>peruſing</hi> this, his <hi>after-worke,</hi> which by Gods <hi>providence,</hi> comeing to my hands, I thought my ſelfe bound in conſcience, to impart vnto thee.</p>
            <p>I pray <hi>God</hi> the reading it, may ſo worke with thee, that, if thou be a <hi>minister,</hi> it may either reforme thee; or incourage thee; according as, thou art either <hi>lyable</hi> to the <hi>reproofe,</hi> or, <hi>capable</hi> of the <hi>comfort</hi> herein contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: or, if thou be a private <hi>Christian,</hi> it may both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get, &amp; increaſe in thee, a reverence, to the <hi>ministers</hi> of God: &amp; ſuch a deepe <hi>detestation,</hi> of theiſe <hi>enormous</hi> corruptions, heere taxed: that thou mayſt become a daylie <hi>ſuttour,</hi> at the <hi>throne</hi> of grace, that the <hi>Lord,</hi> for his owne name ſake, and for his poore <hi>churches</hi> ſake, would vouchſafe, ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity to reforme them, Amen! <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>
            </p>
            <div type="postscript">
               <pb facs="tcp:17442:4"/>
               <head>A poſt-ſcript to the Reader.</head>
               <p>CVrteous <hi>Reader,</hi> we muſt renew the common, and ordinarie <hi>requeſt,</hi> at thy hands: namely, to conceive the better, of ſuch, as had the <hi>peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,</hi> and <hi>printing</hi> this <hi>Sermon:</hi> when thou shalt meete with ſome few places therein (for they are not many) more difficult, then can be wel vnderſtood: &amp; other, petty, ſmall faults, of the <hi>preſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the one, know, the <hi>Coppy</hi> came to vs miſerably written, which therefore craved a neceſſitie of <hi>retranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribing,</hi> wherein were ſome places hard to be read: yet being loth, to leave out any ſentence, or peice of a ſentence, which we could make <hi>English</hi> of, we put ſome words downe, at a <hi>venture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the other, know, that it was printed, where, our <hi>language</hi> is a ſtranger: and by ſuch, as could neither vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand nor ſpeake the ſame: and therefore, it could not be, but that more then ordinarie ſlips, and <hi>ſolaeciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes,</hi> in our tongue, muſt be committed: but ſticke not thou, at theiſe triffling errours; make vſe of the ſolid, and ſubſtantiall matter, thou shalt find in the worke: and give God the glory of his owne trueth, tho in the light thereof, a little obſcured, with the <hi>motes,</hi> of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more frailety, from shining, altogether ſo cleerely to thee. Fare well.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17442:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> Fruitfull Sermon preached by a faithfull ſervant of God, &amp; minister of the goſpell at a generall viſitation.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>The text</hi> Col. 4.<hi>17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And ſay to <hi>Archippus,</hi> take heede to the miniſterie, which thou haſt received in the <hi>Lord,</hi> that thou fulfill it.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in the <hi>first</hi> part of the Epiſtle had ſett downe the ſumme of the Chriſtian doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, &amp; therein ſhewed what <hi>Chriſt</hi> was, both concerning his perſon, &amp; his office, &amp; how we are made partakers of the benefits of both; &amp; in the <hi>ſecond</hi> part thereof had diſputed with the falſe Apoſtles, &amp; confuted their falſe doctrine &amp; corruptions: &amp; in the <hi>third</hi> place had ſett downe precepts concerning manners &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations to a Chriſtian, adding in the end of all, freindly &amp; brotherly ſalutations: he comes to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish them of a duty which they were to performes to <hi>Archippus</hi> their miniſter, in theiſe words. <hi>Say to</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chippus <hi>take heede to the ministerie &amp;c.</hi> It appeareth by theiſe words that <hi>Archippus</hi> was a miniſter of the church at <hi>Coloſsia;</hi> &amp; becauſe he was negligent in his dutye, or at leaſt not ſo diligent &amp; faithfull as both he should &amp; might have beene, he therefore willeth the <hi>Coloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> to admonish him of his fault, &amp; to ſtirre him vp to a carefull diſ-ſcharge of his miniſterie. <hi>Say to</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chippus <hi>take heede to the ministerie &amp;c.</hi> As if he should
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17442:5"/>
have ſaide: be vigilant &amp; circumſpect, be carefull &amp; watchfull, diligently conſider, &amp; marke earneſtly what thy calling is, &amp; of what great accounte it is: it is the miniſterie, the preaching of the word, the inſtructing of the people, which thou haſt received, not of <hi>man,</hi> but of the <hi>Lord:</hi> both, <hi>of</hi> the Lord who is the authour of the miniſterie, &amp; <hi>for</hi> the Lord who is the end of the miniſterie. Thou haſt received it <hi>by his grace,</hi> thou haſt received it <hi>for his glory;</hi> let not this grace be in vaine in thee, let not this glory be neglected by thee but ſo walke in thy miniſterie that thou fulfill it: ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve &amp; perfect, &amp; finiſh, &amp; diſcharge that charge, which is layde vpon thee. The ſumme then of theiſe words is a rouſing of negligent miniſters: wherein we may note <hi>two</hi> things: <hi>first,</hi> the perſons comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to doe this duty. <hi>Secondly,</hi> the manner how, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely by exhortation, wherein obſerve <hi>two</hi> things further.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> wherevnto they muſt exhort him to a ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of his miniſterie. <hi>Secondly,</hi> the reaſon whereby they ſtirre him vp to the ſame drawne from the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of God who is the authour of the miniſterie. Thou haſt received it in the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Say to</hi> Archippus:] who muſt ſay to <hi>Archippus</hi> thus, namely the <hi>Coloſsians</hi> to whome <hi>Paul</hi> writeth. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is the dutye of the people to admonish the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of his miniſterie,<note place="margin">Doct. 1.</note> &amp; to put him in mind of the diſcharge of his dutye if he be negligent therein. For otherwiſe <hi>Paul</hi> might have admonished <hi>Archippus</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by writing vnto him ſome particular letter, but in that he biddeth the <hi>Coloſsians</hi> to doe it, he sheweth it a dutye belonging to the people to <hi>iogg</hi> their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter in the ellbowe as it were, to put him in mind of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17442:5"/>
his charge, &amp; bid him remember his office &amp; miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie &amp; by exhortation to excite &amp; ſtirre him vp to a faithfull diſ-charge of his dutye.</p>
            <p>A ſtrange &amp; vnreaſonable doctrine may ſome men ſaye; for what should the <hi>stones</hi> come tumbling out of the quarrie, and ſaye to the <hi>builder</hi> come cutt me and ſquare me, and hew me thus? or should the <hi>tree</hi> come dauncing out of the wood and ſay to the <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter</hi> cutt me and plaine me, or frame me thus, or thus; that I may be fit for the building? what shall the <hi>sheepe</hi> come to the <hi>ſhepheard</hi> and put him in mind of his dutye? So, should the people come and admonish the miniſter, and tell him of his miniſterie? right even ſoe;<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.5.</note> for they are no <hi>dead</hi> ſtones that lie in the quarrie, but as <hi>Peter</hi> calleth them they are <hi>living stones</hi> which can turne themſelves to the hammer, and <hi>trees of righteouſnes</hi> (as the Prophet calleth them) which offer themſelves to the <hi>Carpenter:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 61.3.</note> they are <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable sheepe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> which can bring their cauſe to the <hi>Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard.</hi> Their ſoules are committed to the care of the miniſter to be taught and inſtructed, and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and therefore as they regard their owne ſoules and ſalvations, they muſt regard the miniſters dutye. As was the caſe of that ship which was covered with waves when <hi>Christ</hi> was a ſleepe, ſuch is the caſe of a congregation when the miniſter is idle and negligent, as lulled a ſleepe in the cradle of ſecuritie. The diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples feared leſt through <hi>Christs</hi> ſleepeing, they should have been <hi>drownea:</hi> and that congregation may feare leſt through their Paſtours negligence, it be <hi>damned.</hi> Therefore as then the diſciples, in love of their lives went to <hi>Christ</hi> and a woke him: ſo it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooveth the people for love of their ſoules to goe to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17442:6"/>
their <hi>Paſtour,</hi> and awake him, and ſtirre him vp that he looke about him. In other matters we are carefull to put him in mind with whome we deale to deale faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie with vs, and shall we be leſſe carefull in this which is the maine pointe? In the hand of the <hi>Miller</hi> we looſe but our meale, of the <hi>Farrier</hi> but our horſe, of the <hi>Taylour</hi> but our garment, of the <hi>Lawyer</hi> but our money, of the <hi>Phyſition</hi> but our bodyes: but in the hands of an vnfaithfull miniſter a man looſeth his ſoule and his everlaſting portion in heaven. If then we ſay to the <hi>Miller,</hi> looke to my meale: to the <hi>Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier,</hi> have a care of my horſe: to the <hi>Taylour,</hi> ſpoyle not my garment: to the <hi>Lawyer,</hi> tender my caſe: to the <hi>Phyſition,</hi> regard my health: how much more should we ſay vnto the <hi>minister</hi> (if he be vnfaithfull) looke to ourſoules <hi>&amp; take heede to the ministerie which thou hast received in the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Kings 4 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>[When the <hi>Shunamites</hi> ſonne was dead shee went to the <hi>Prophet</hi> to tell him of it that he might come and reſtore her dead ſonne to life againe: the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſent his ſervant <hi>Gehazi,</hi> with a ſtaffe but shee would not be content with that but tooke holde of him and would not leave him, but he himſelfe muſt come. As carefull as the <hi>Shunamite</hi> was for her dead child: ſo carefull ought the people to be for their dead ſoules: as shee went to the <hi>Prophet</hi> to have her dead ſonne rayſed: ſo muſt they to their miniſter to have their dead ſoules quickened. As shee did not content her ſelfe with the <hi>Prophets</hi> ſervant but tooke hold of the <hi>Prophet</hi> hinſelfe ſo muſt the people not content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with ignorant ſubſtitutes of others, but take hold of the Paſtour himſelfe and he shall have enough to recover their dead ſoules to life, though he goeth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17442:6"/>
himſelfe, and putteth mouth to mouth.</p>
            <p>This being the dutie of the people toward their miniſter to bid him take heede to his miniſterie what if I should expoſtulate with you that are to your <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister,</hi> as theiſe <hi>Coloſsians</hi> to <hi>Archippus?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vſe.</note> Tell me you that complaine of your miniſter that he is ignorant, or negligent, or vnfaithfull, did you ever ſay vnto him take heed to thy miniſterie! did you ever ſtirre him vp, and incite him therevnto? alas no! your owne conſciences tell you that you have failed heerein! &amp; there hath been both in the miniſter toward you: &amp; in you toward the miniſter, a careleſnes by conſent each with other: <hi>he,</hi> not regarding whither he did diſ-charg his miniſterie or no: and <hi>you,</hi> not careing whither you did admonish him or no, and thus <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chippus</hi> hath been long a-ſleepe becauſe the <hi>Coloſsians</hi> did not awake him. Thus the miniſters have neglec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their dutyes becauſe you have not ſaid to them as heere the <hi>Coloſsians</hi> muſt ſay to <hi>Archippus</hi> take heed to the miniſterie &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Say to Archippus</hi>]</p>
            <p>The <hi>Coloſsians</hi> muſt admonish <hi>Archippus</hi> and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chippus</hi> muſt be content to be admonished of the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſsians.</hi> Therefore.</p>
            <p>The <hi>minister</hi> muſt not refuſe to be admonished,<note place="margin">Doct. 1.</note> &amp; put in mind of his dutye by the <hi>people</hi> whome he should teach: but as it is his dutie to teach others, ſo he muſt shew himſelfe teachable, and willing to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed of others: ſtill remembring though honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable his calling be, excellent his authoritie, great his power, yet he is not exempted from lawes, nor privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged from the admonition of his people, but both may and when occaſion is offered muſt be admonis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17442:7"/>
even of them that are as inferiour to him, as the <hi>Coloſsians</hi> were to <hi>Archippus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Kings 5</note> As when <hi>Elisha</hi> comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Naaman</hi> to wash himſelfe ſeven times in <hi>Iordan</hi> he turned about in a ſnuffe, &amp; went away in diſpleaſure, but his ſervant came vnto him and ſaid: Father if the Prophet had commanded thee a greater matter, wouldſt thou not have done it? how much more, when he ſaith vnto thee wash and be cleane. Then went he downe &amp; washed himſelfe,<note place="margin">2. Kings 5.13.14.</note> and was clenſed. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if this noble man had diſdeined the admonition of his ſervant, he would have continued a leaper ſtill, and had never been cleenſed: ſo if the miniſters in the pride of hearte should ſcorne the admonition of their poore <hi>Parishioners,</hi> ſurely they should continue negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent ſtill, and would never be reformed. Therefore as he with a good hearte endured the voyce of his ſervants, and did as they counſelled him: So shall it be good for you (<hi>men and brethren</hi> as many as are negligent in your duties) to heare the admonition of your people, and to obey them. <hi>Moſes</hi> that man of <hi>God,</hi> though indued with the <hi>H. Ghoſt,</hi> though magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with the guift of workeing wonders, though ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with <hi>policie,</hi> and managing matters of ſtate, as may ſeeme by his bringing vp in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> courte, yet diſdeined he not to be better inſtructed in the manner of good government by <hi>Iethro,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 18.17.</note> inferiour to himſelfe. The eye cannot ſaye to the foote I have no neede of thee, nor the head to the hand I have no neede of thee, nor the <hi>Pastour</hi> to the <hi>people</hi> in matter of admonition, I have no neede of you. Away then with that proud, haughtie and diſdeinfull mind that is not ashamed to be negligent in his miniſterie and yet ſcorneth to be admonished of his people, and to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17442:7"/>
be put in mind of his miniſterie? awaye then with theiſe ſcornefull ſpeeches (the very ſignes &amp; tokens of a proud hearte) shall I be reprooved by him? or shall a <hi>taylour</hi> or <hi>ſhooe-maker</hi> come and tell me my dutie? a <hi>hatter</hi> or <hi>mercer</hi> or ſuch like, admonish me of my mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie? why, I doubt not but among theiſe <hi>Coloſsians,</hi> there were both <hi>taylours</hi> and <hi>ſhooe-makers,</hi> and of moſt occupations, and yet doeth <hi>Paul</hi> will them to tell <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chippus</hi> of his dutie: &amp; without doubt he would faine have <hi>Archippus</hi> contented there withall.</p>
            <p>Therefore let vs of the miniſterie ſend home this pride to the <hi>Eldest ſonne of pride,</hi> the <hi>beast of Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vſe.</note> that <hi>man of ſinne</hi> that <hi>child of perdition,</hi> whoe ſitteth in his chaire of miſcheife, mooveth like an <hi>oracle,</hi> and both thinketh in his heart, and ſpeaketh with his mouth, that no man may ſay to him: <hi>Domine quid it à facis! Sir,</hi> why doe you thus? let vs rather remember that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollos</hi> though an eloquent man &amp; mightie in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, though fervent in ſpirit, and a diligent Preacher, yet he refuſed not to be taught more perfectly the waye of the Lord by <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 18, 25.26.</note> an handy craft man, a poore tent-maker, nay of <hi>Priſcilla</hi> a woe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and wife of <hi>Aquila.</hi> And if he was contented to be taught, &amp; inſtructed of them in his dutye, let none of vs diſdeine to be admonished, or ſtirred vp in his dutye by thoſe that are committed to our charge.</p>
            <p>Thus much of the perſons admonishing and ſuch as are to be admonished; now of the admonition it ſelfe. <hi>Take heede to the miniſterie which thou hast recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in ye Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This miniſterie which he muſt take heede vnto, conteineth all the dutyes of the miniſters of God, which may be referred to theiſe generall heads.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:17442:8"/>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 28.19.20.</note>
               <hi>Firſt</hi> to the <hi>preaching of the word. Goe pteach the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell,</hi> have a care and regard that all the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be kept teaching them to obſerve all things whatſoever I commande you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly</hi> to the <hi>adminiſtration of the Sacraments. Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing them in the name of the Father, the Sonne, and the H. Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> to <hi>private inſpection</hi> by reprooveing Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners by admonishing, exhorting, by comforting the afflicted &amp; thoſe which are caſt downe, &amp; all to this end, that the elect whome ſinne hath looſened, &amp; dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynted from <hi>Chriſt</hi> their head, may be reſtored to their place againe: joyned both <hi>to Chriſt</hi> their head by the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and one to another by love, which is it <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes of <hi>Epheſ. 4.</hi>12.</p>
            <p>That alſo (ſaith he) the bodie of <hi>Chriſt</hi> may be edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and built vp, and come vnto a perfect man in <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Which shall then be, when all the elect shalbe gathered together by the miniſterie of the word: which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> there calleth <hi>the worke of the miniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie,</hi> not an <hi>idlenes,</hi> but a <hi>worke,</hi> not a <hi>lordlines,</hi> but a <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This dutye may further be ſeene by the titles which are given to the miniſters in the Scriptures.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> They are <hi>Paſtours</hi> and therefore their dutye is to feede the people of <hi>God</hi> that dependeth vpon them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.9</note>They are <hi>Huſband-men</hi> and therefore in duty muſt till <hi>Gods</hi> ground, and ſowe his ſeede.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1.17.</note>They are <hi>VVatchmen</hi> and therefore muſt give the people warning of enſuing danger.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor 4.1</note>They are <hi>diſpencers of the myſteries of God</hi> to deliver that to the people which they have received of him. Called <hi>ſtewards</hi> of <hi>Gods</hi> howſe,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and therefore muſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17442:8"/>
give everie man his portion of meate in due ſeaſon.</p>
            <p>They are the <hi>light of the world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5.14.</note> and therefore their duty is to shine forth by heavenly doctrine to enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>Gods</hi> people.</p>
            <p>They are the <hi>Salt of the earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5.13.</note> and therefore their dutie is to ſeaſon with wholeſome doctrine, the weake ſoules that bend to corruption.</p>
            <p>They are <hi>builders,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.10</note> and therefore muſt edifie the body of <hi>Christ,</hi> the howſe of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They are <hi>Captaines,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13.17.</note> and therefore it is their part to fight <hi>Gods</hi> battailes: and as good <hi>leaders</hi> and <hi>cheife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teines</hi> to inſtruct Gods people well in this ſpirituall warfare.</p>
            <p>They are called <hi>Embaſſadours,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 6.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and therefore their dutye is to declare <hi>Gods</hi> meſſage to the people.</p>
            <p>And all this is but their <hi>ministerie,</hi> now for the full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling and diſ-charge of this miniſterie, two things are required.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt <hi>Knowledge.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly <hi>faithfullnes.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt that he be <hi>able,</hi> and ſecondly that he be <hi>care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi> and diligent to teach <hi>Gods</hi> people. Concerning the firſt, the miniſter of God muſt not be onely as a <hi>Spence or store-howſe,</hi> wherein <hi>God</hi> hath layd vp know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as a good howſe-holder doeth Corne in a <hi>gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> ſignified by that in the Prophecie of <hi>Malachie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 2.7.</note> that the Preiſts lips muſt preſerve knowledge, and for want thereof God hath divorced him from the honour of the miniſterie, and hath pronounced him to be no Preiſt for him, becauſe thou haſt refuſed knowledge,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 4.6.</note> I will alſo refuſe thee thou shalt be no Preiſt to me.</p>
            <p>But he muſt have the wiſdome of a wiſe ſteward,<note place="margin">Luc. 12.24.</note> that knowes how to give Gods children, or howſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17442:9"/>
their portion of meate in due ſeaſon as <hi>Christ</hi> ſpeakes: miniſtring milke to thoſe that are but babes, and yonglings in Chriſt, and ſtrong meate to thoſe of riper age.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.15.</note>He muſt be one that can divide the word of truth aright, being as skilfull in divideing the word of <hi>God,</hi> as the <hi>Levites</hi> were in cutting a broad the beaſt for ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, whence that phraſe of <hi>divideing the word</hi> ſeemes to be borrowed. He muſt not onely be learned him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,<note place="margin">1. Ti. 3.2.</note> but which is more, apt and fit to teach others as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes. This skilfulnes of the miniſter in tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching others was ſignified in the <hi>old</hi> Teſtament, not onely by that <hi>urim &amp; Thummim</hi> on the breſt-plate to <hi>ſignifie</hi> his knowledge and holines:<note place="margin">Ex. 28.30.</note> but alſo by the <hi>bells</hi> which did hang on the skirts of the <hi>Preists</hi> gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 33.</note> meaning as by the <hi>Pomegranates</hi> he should ſmell ſweetely with the odours of a good life, ſo by the <hi>bells</hi> that he should ſound vnto others by prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of true doctrine, by the ſound of which bells he was to be heard when he went into the holy place, &amp; when he came out vpon paine of death. And what els in the <hi>N. Teſtament</hi> did the <hi>H. Ghost</hi> in the likenes of tongues ſignifie? he deſcended vpon the Apoſtles, not in the likenes of hands,<note place="margin">Act. 2.3.</note> whereby to overcome the world by wordly feare, nor of feete, whereby to flee from the rage of perſequuting ennimies, nor of eyes and eares fitt inſtruments to learne: but in the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of tongues, to teach the people their dutye in being the tongues of God to them. And what els doe all their names declare, being ſo many arguments to enforce this pointe? For how can they be called <hi>light,</hi> if being darke themſelves they cannot ſend out the blaze of true th to enlighten others? Or <hi>ſalt</hi> of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17442:9"/>
earth, if being vnſavourie themſelves they cannot ſeaſon &amp; preſerve <hi>Gods</hi> people from ſinne and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption? Or <hi>Pastours</hi> if they cannot feede the flocke of Chriſt with the foode of life? Or <hi>Huſband-men</hi> and cannot plowe <hi>Gods</hi> ground, and ſowe his feede? Or <hi>Stewards</hi> if they cannot, or doe not rule his howſehold? Or <hi>Meſſengers</hi> and <hi>Ambaſſadours</hi> if they cannot ſpeake in his name and declare his meſſage, and ambaſſage vnto his people? Or <hi>builders</hi> if they cannot build vp <hi>Gods</hi> ſpirituall howſe? Or <hi>Capteines</hi> if they knowe not how to fight Gods <hi>battailes.</hi> Neither let any man thinke that if a miniſter be able to reade he hath ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient knowledge,<note place="margin">Mat. 9.36.</note> and that <hi>bare readers</hi> are ſufficient miniſters, Chriſt greived to ſee the multitude diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as sheepe without Shepheards, and yet had they Moſes read in their Synagogues even every Sabaoth day, and the Prophets, as may be gathered by Luke in the Acts.<note place="margin">Act. 13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Implying that <hi>readers</hi> were no ſufficient <hi>Pastours,</hi> for els the <hi>Iewes</hi> in their <hi>Synagogues</hi> (as we have in our churches) had not ben without Paſtours and ſo not ſo miſerable, as he greived they were, when he conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered what was requiſite in a miniſter, namely to bring back that which is gone a ſtraye, and to preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve from daunger, to heale the broken, to bind vp the wounded, and the like. For which cauſe he ſends his Apoſtles, by their preaching to performe that which they by their reading, could not doe. And if to have the law and the Prophets read had been enough, then had the Iewes knowne Chriſt, for Moſes wrote of him Ioh. 5.39.46.<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.39, 46.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And among the Prophets, Eſay <hi>ſo</hi> plainely that Ierome ſticks not to call him an <hi>Evangelicke</hi> and yet
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17442:10"/>
the <hi>noble-man</hi> when he read Eſay could not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand,<note place="margin">Act. 8.30.31.</note> but he was in neede of <hi>Philip</hi> to come &amp; preach vnto him, and to inſtruct him. And if this inſtruction did not neede, but that the ignorant by <hi>bare reading,</hi> might vnderſtand the meaning of the word (which yet is impoſſible) yet theiſe of greateſt knowledge may, and often be ſo overtaken, and ſurprized with paſſions &amp; infirmities, that they have neede of others (by applying of the word) to heale their diſeaſes. Whither <hi>Moſes</hi> were read in <hi>Davids</hi> time we cannot certainely affirme, yet certaine it is that <hi>David</hi> whoſe whole delight and ſtudy was in the law of God as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares Pſal. 119. was well skilled therein: ſo that his knowledg would ſerve him to conclude, that he hath committed murder and adulterie, and as ſure as God lived, was the child of God and yet he had need of Nathan to applye this word vnto him, and to tell him <hi>he was the man.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. ſam. 12.</note> So that we ſee how neceſſarie it is that a miniſter should have, <hi>not knowledge to read onely</hi> (for that children, and woemen have) but to preach, and alſo to apply the word to the ſoules and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of the hearer.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Vſe.</note>The more lamentable is the ſtate of the church in whome-ſoever the fault lieth, whither in them that should provide ſufficient living, and will not, as it is in ſome <hi>Parishes,</hi> or in them that should make ſufficient miniſters, and doe not as in ſome <hi>Bishops:</hi> or in them that should preſent able Paſtours, and care not, as in ſome <hi>Patrones. But</hi> in whomeſoever the faulte is, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable is their ſtate, that are yet as <hi>sheepe</hi> without a <hi>shepheard,</hi> as an <hi>army</hi> of ſimple <hi>Souldiours</hi> without a <hi>conducteur.</hi> If the eſtate of Iſrael was in danger, when through the <hi>tyrannie</hi> of the <hi>Philistines,</hi> even in the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17442:10"/>
dayes of battaile, there was neither ſpeare, nor ſword found in the hand of any of the people, but onely in the hand of <hi>Saul,</hi> and <hi>Ionathan:</hi> how, <hi>not dangerous,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. ſam. 13.22.</note> but <hi>almost deſperate,</hi> is the eſtate of any thouſands of our people, who not onely themſelves are vn-armed of the knowledge of God, but even <hi>Saul</hi> &amp; <hi>Ionathan</hi> toe, even the <hi>leaders</hi> and <hi>Commanders</hi> want the armour of God, and skill how to vſe it, even the miniſters them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves want the knowledge of Gods word, and skill how to preach it.<note place="margin">Numb 4.2.</note> What marvell then though the people perish? The Lord commanded that the <hi>Arke</hi> should be carried by none but <hi>Levites,</hi> for ſo he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, and David repeates it, <hi>none (ſaith he) ought to carry the Arke of the Lord but the Levites.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. chro. 15 2.</note> 
               <hi>For the Lord had choſen</hi> them to beare the <hi>Arke</hi> of the Lord, and to miniſter to him for ever, therefore when this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God was not obſerved, but the <hi>Arke</hi> was put vpon the <hi>Cart,</hi> and drawen by <hi>Oxen,</hi> the <hi>Oxen</hi> did shake it,<note place="margin">2. ſam. 6.</note> and the <hi>Arke</hi> of God had almoſt fallen to the ground: right ſo hath God commanded that the care of the <hi>church</hi> should be vpon the shoulders of <hi>preaching ministers</hi> onely, and if this ordinance be not obſerved, but neglected, (as we ſee it is) and the arke be drawne by oxen, the care of the church be committed to ignorant men, voyde of ſound know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, skandalous to the word, the diſ-grace of the miniſterie, the bane of religion, and the shame of the church, what may we looke for, but the daunger of a great downe-fall, ſurely the oxen will shake it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſo feared the hurt, and regarded the good of his Cattell, as that he thought none fitt to be their ruler, but men knowne to be men of activitie,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.7.</note> for ſo he ſpeaketh, if thou knoweſt that there be men of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17442:11"/>
activitie, make them rulers over my cattell: ſpeakeing to <hi>Ioſeph</hi> concerning his brethren. And shall <hi>Pharaohs</hi> cattell have men of activitie, and shall not Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have men of knowledge? will <hi>Pharaoh</hi> have none to be his <hi>Cow-heards</hi> but men skillfull in that trade? and shall we thinke men of no learning fit to guide, and teach Gods people, which is a trade of trades and an art of artes? If we be to travell we ſeeke the chei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt men of skill to direct vs, if to goe by ſea, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the beſt <hi>Pilot</hi> to conduct vs, if we be ſicke we wish for the moſt excellent <hi>Phyſitian</hi> to cure vs: and shall we be ſo ſence-les, and infatuated, as to thinke any miniſter (be he never ſo ignorant) good enough to teach vs? if you thinke ſo, then looke and behold the miſerie that is vpon the mounteine of <hi>Samaria,</hi> behold the blacke countreyes of <hi>ignorance</hi> yet among vs, voyde of the light of Gods word! how many of our land are compaſſed with confuſion of hellish darknes as a people vowed to deſtruction! how many be like <hi>dragons</hi> and <hi>ſerpents</hi> in the deepe caves of the earth! how many ſleepe in ignorance like <hi>Molles</hi> and <hi>battes</hi> in the holes! how many as the <hi>Aſsyrians</hi> in <hi>Samaria,</hi> who know not the <hi>manner</hi> of the God of our land, whoſe eſtate is blacke and <hi>a diſmall</hi> day vpon them, vnleſſe God ſend them <hi>Pastours</hi> after his owne heart, which may feede them with knowledg, and vnderſtanding; the want whereof let the <hi>Popish idolatrie</hi> and groſſe <hi>ſuperstition,</hi> let the <hi>heathenish, prophane,</hi> and <hi>palpable</hi> blindnes of the common people, their vnreverent, &amp; irreligious behaviour in things concerning God, let their <hi>Sybaritical</hi> feaſts and banquets conſecrated to <hi>Flora, Criſpin, Clement</hi> and <hi>Bacchus,</hi> and ſuch <hi>bouzing</hi> drunken Patrones, let the exceſſe, and moſt lothſome
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17442:11"/>
vomit of <hi>whitſon-ale,</hi> and <hi>Pentecost</hi> Lords; let the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of poperie into <hi>England</hi> againe, with a maine ſtreame, as of the <hi>Romanes</hi> into <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> ſpeake and cry alowde in your hearts and eares: and moove you to inward pitty and compaſſion of Gods <hi>church.</hi> And as for you which entred into this calling, and have not knowledg to diſ-charge your calling, I ſay not as the <hi>Coloſsians</hi> to <hi>Archippus,</hi> take heed to your mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie, but take heede of the danger, which you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre by ſtarveing Gods vnſpotted lambs, with gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den fleeces. <hi>Remember,</hi> that you have not the charge of oxen, sheepe, but of the moſt brittell, and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous things in the world, even the ſoules of men that are ready to be mooved by every temptation: of tho moſt choyce and precious things in the world bought with the greateſt price, even the blood of Chriſt, whoſe charge is ſo great that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> well weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame, crieth out as a man vnder a heavy burden; and <hi>who is ſufficient for theiſe things?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 2.16.</note> and if he being qualified from above, haveing excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t guifts of the ſpirit, did ſo highly eſteeme of the ſame, as to judge himſelfe inſufficient for al that: what baſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite had you of the miniſterie? how eaſy did you deeme it to be, when you entred thereinto! no man will preſume to teach an art before he have learned it himſelfe. Conſider how you diſ-grace the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie, and the profeſſion of <hi>divine</hi> ſtudies, by your <hi>ignorance.</hi> For as in times paſt the people haveing a <hi>Ghost</hi> in great admiration, thought that to be wanting in the religion, which was wanting in him; ſo the people which follow you to be inſtructed by you, ſeeing the lamentable lookes of your ignorance, thinke that to be wanting in the miniſter, which is
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17442:12"/>
wanting in you. <hi>Conſider</hi> the great danger both of your ſelves, and the people whome by <hi>your</hi> ignoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce you keepe in continuall ignorance, and therefore both may feare that fearfull doome pronounced by <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">mat. 15.14.</note> 
               <hi>If the blind leade the blind, both shall fall into the ditch.</hi> If <hi>Bezaleel</hi> and <hi>Aholiah</hi> when they were to worke in the tabernacle, had not knowledge enough (though they were work-men before) but had neede to be filled with the Spirit of God in wiſdome,<note place="margin">Exod. 31.2.3, 6.</note> and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, in knowledg and workman-ship: then much more thinke you in the ſecrets of your hearts, what knowledge is required of you who worke not in an earthly <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> but in the building vp a <hi>temple</hi> for <hi>God</hi> to dwell more ſpeciallie in, even in the hearts of the people, in reareing vp a <hi>chaire</hi> of eſtate for Chriſt Ieſus to ſitt &amp; rule in, even in the conſciences of men, and in frameing a <hi>ſchoole</hi> for Chriſt to teach even in the ſoules of men? Sitt downe and conſider that which Chriſt shewed, before you entred into this calling, to be conſidered of, whither you be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently armed to meete your enimies that come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you: if not, let not ten <hi>shekels</hi> and a <hi>ſute</hi> of appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, and meate and drinke, which was the wages <hi>Micha</hi> gave to his wandring <hi>curate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. 17.10.</note> that went vp and downe to ſeeke a ſervice, nay let not a thowſand <hi>times</hi> ſo much prevaile with you to incourage you heerein, as the feare of that fearefull ſpeech terrifie you: when you admonish not a wicked man of his wickednes. Nay, that wicked man shall die in his ſinns, but his blood will I require at thy hands.<note place="margin">Ezek. 3.18.</note> So that if any perish through ignorance, your ſoule ſtandeth for their ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, both shall go to <hi>hell</hi> together, therefore <hi>take heede to your ministerie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:17442:12"/>The <hi>ſecond</hi> thing which the miniſterie requireth at a miniſters hand, is, not onely that he be <hi>skilfull,</hi> but alſo <hi>faithfull</hi> &amp; <hi>watchfull,</hi> which,<note place="margin">Luke 12.42. Act. 20.20. Tim. 4.2.</note> as Chriſt commanded in a <hi>Steward</hi> that gives his howſe-hold meate in due ſeaſon, ſo Paul practiſed as a faithful Steward, teaching openly, and in every howſe, laying it to the charge of Timothie, with witnes, ſaying: <hi>I charge thee before God, and before the Lord Ieſus Christ, Who shal judge the quicke, and the dead at the day of his appearing, and in his kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Preach,</hi> that is his office, <hi>be instant in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon,</hi> that is the time. In ſeaſon to them that will, out of ſeaſon to them that will not. How? reproove exhort, correct, with al long-ſuffring, and doctrine, that is the manner.</p>
            <p>And this duty Chriſt enjoyned Peter vnto,<note place="margin">Ioh. 21.1.</note> he ſayth not, be thou a <hi>Paſtour,</hi> or a <hi>Bishop,</hi> or a <hi>Prelate,</hi> but feede thou becauſe many Paſtours in name, are but <hi>idoles</hi> in deede, which either devoure them, or fleece them,<note place="margin">Mat. 9.3.</note> but feede them not. Therefore ſayth Chriſt the harveſt is greate, and there are, what few few Prelates, few mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, or few learned men? no, but there are few la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers, few workemen.</p>
            <p>Wherevnto ſerveth that of the Apoſtle. <hi>If any man deſireth the office of a Bishop, or a minister he deſireth a good worke</hi> a good <hi>dutie,</hi> not a good <hi>dignitie,</hi> not a good delight, not good riches, not good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venews, but a good worke.</p>
            <p>And to this end were <hi>Aaron,</hi> and his ſonnes <hi>anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> not onely to be <hi>Preists</hi> to the Lord and to ſtand as many do like <hi>Cyphres</hi> in <hi>Augrum;</hi> but to execute the Preiſt-hood and as the phraſe is often repeated, to ſerve in the Preiſts office before the <hi>Lord. So that,</hi> a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17442:13"/>
miniſter muſt not onely be skilfull in his miniſterie, but faithfull and diligent, and painefull, in his miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: and conſider the <hi>faithfulnes</hi> of Iacob in keeping <hi>Labans</hi> sheepe <hi>I was</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>conſumed with heate, and the froſt by night, and my ſleepe departed from mine eyes.</hi> If he be <hi>ſo</hi> carefull for Labans sheepe: how much more carefull &amp; watchfull should we be for the <hi>sheepe</hi> of Gods fold and feare neither the <hi>pinching</hi> cold of adverſitie, nor the <hi>parching</hi> heate of perſequuting <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants</hi> to procure their good.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Chr 18: 14.15.16.</note>We may reade in the booke of Chronicles, that in Davids howſe there were Officers appointed to everie charge: particular Officers for his <hi>treaſures,</hi> for his <hi>sheepe,</hi> for his <hi>vines</hi> &amp;c. that no man should be oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with too great charge, but that everie man should be carefull, and faithfull in his place. So in Gods howſe hath he appointed particular officers. And what are Davids treaſures to the Lords? Gods trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is Davids heart, and Davids treaſure but duſt: Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid himſelfe one of Gods sheepe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Davids sheepe ſimple beaſts: David is a branch of Gods vine, and Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids vines but vanitie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe. 2.</note>Then this is <hi>just reproofe</hi> to all ſuch to whome the Lord hath given <hi>gifts</hi> fit to teach &amp; yet are negligent, and idle, and ſlothfull, and will not teach being like faithles <hi>Capteines</hi> who receive continuallie the Lords <hi>pay,</hi> and yet never fight the Lords <hi>battailes</hi> whoſe knowledge is wrapt vp in an idle braine without prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe as <hi>Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ahs</hi> ſword in cloth without uſe.<note place="margin">2. ſam. 12.5. Prov. 11.26,</note> If the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple curſe him that with-drawes his <hi>Corne</hi> from the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket: how much more shall they be curſed, who by keepeing the corne of Gods word, from the <hi>congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of his people, bring vpon themſelves ſo fearefull
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17442:13"/>
a ſinne? Who when as they should by preaching the word, <hi>distill</hi> on the people, as the <hi>dew</hi> vpon the graſſe, and as the <hi>raine</hi> vpon the hearbes, (like <hi>clowdes</hi> which ſweate themſelves to death) vanish away in vanitie, like <hi>brests</hi> without milke, and <hi>clowdes</hi> without water, who when they should in the <hi>wombe</hi> of the <hi>church,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gett many <hi>children</hi> of glory to God, deſerved to be <hi>fined</hi> of our <hi>Gouvernours</hi> as the <hi>old</hi> and <hi>ſingle</hi> men of <hi>Rome</hi> were by their <hi>Cenſors</hi> caſt out becauſe they brought no children to the <hi>common-wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now hearken what the Lord ſaith to the <hi>idle</hi> of <hi>idole</hi> shephearde. Thus ſaith the Lord God vnto the shepheards of Iſrael that doe feed themſelves:<note place="margin">Ezek. 34.2.</note> should not the shepheards feed the flockes? there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith the Lord I wil come againſt the shepheard, and will require my sheepe at their hands: and his blood that dieth without warning will I require at the watch-mans hands. For what, should the <hi>Porter</hi> ſleepe when the <hi>theefe</hi> ſeekes to enter? Or the <hi>Pilot</hi> be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les when the <hi>ship</hi> is in danger? Or the <hi>Capteine</hi> ſecure when the <hi>enimie</hi> is at hand? Or the miniſter be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligent, when his people be ignorant, and like to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish for want of viſion? and the devill readie to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroye at all advantages? Far be it! for what were this, but even to betraye Gods people into the hands of Pirats, theeves, and robbers?</p>
            <p>But what shall we ſay to them that have a cure of ſoules in one place, and live in another: like fugitive Capteines forſake their Enſigne and Company at <hi>Barwicke</hi> &amp; flee to <hi>Dover</hi> who being with Ionah com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded for <hi>Niniveh,</hi> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e to <hi>Tar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hish:</hi> who being pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the <hi>countrie,</hi> run to the <hi>univerſitie.</hi> Who leave their charge, as the <hi>Ostrrich</hi> doeth her <hi>Eggs</hi> in the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17442:14"/>
earth,<note place="margin">Job 39.17.</note> and ſands: forgetting that either the <hi>ſoote</hi> might ſcatter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or the wild beaſt breake them shewing her ſelfe cruel to her yong ones, as if they were not hers: &amp; is with feare, as if shee travailled in vaine: Or at the leaſt, leaved her <hi>eggs,</hi> as the <hi>Cue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow</hi> doeth, to be hatched of a <hi>ſparron,</hi> or ſome other bird. <hi>Do</hi> they not every how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re feare leſt God should meete the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> where they are, &amp; haſt vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as <hi>Eliab</hi> did to <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. ſam. 17.28.</note> 
               <hi>why cameſt thou dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne hither?</hi> &amp; <hi>with whome hast thou left thoſe few sheepe in the wildernes? Or</hi> feare they not leſt that befall them which befell <hi>David,</hi> who when he fought Gods <hi>battai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> as the ſworne Capteine of God, was <hi>ſecured</hi> from the <hi>ambushes</hi> of Satan and <hi>fortified</hi> againſt the corruption of his owne nature, but when he gave vp the <hi>admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration</hi> to others, without juſt cauſe and ſate himſelfe downe to reſt in Ieruſalem, and was not reſident in his Campe: then was the H. Ghoſt not reſident in his heart but he fell into thoſe groſſe ſinns of adulterie and murder. Or <hi>lastly</hi> feare <hi>theiſe</hi> not loſt in their abſence their <hi>unlearned</hi> and for the moſt part <hi>ungodly</hi> Vi-Curates should bring a great ſinne &amp; conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a great punishment as Aaron the firſt <hi>Vicar</hi> of the <hi>Synagogue</hi> as <hi>Pariſienſis</hi> calleth him (tho a Vicar of Gods owne chuſing) brought on Iſrael who when Moſes had ben abſent from them but onely fourtie dayes, and not as he doeth add in the <hi>Court</hi> with a Prince, nor in the <hi>Pallace</hi> with a Bishop, but in the mount with God: at his returne he found the fooles of Iſrael dauncing a <hi>Morice-dance</hi> about a <hi>Caife.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider then how ignorance irreligious poperie and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanenes, creepeth into the charges of thoſe men who are abſent not fourtie dayes onely as <hi>Moſes</hi> was but fourty weekes together: not with God in any
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17442:14"/>
calling of his, as the ſame Moſes in the mount, but like enough either in the <hi>Court,</hi> or in the <hi>Pallace</hi> as was ſpoken before out of <hi>Pariſienſis:</hi> or els where regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding little their duty Gods glory, or the peoples gooe.</p>
            <p>And to theiſe may be added thoſe, who ſeeking <hi>their owne,</hi> and not that which is Ieſus Chriſts, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to live, and waxe rich with the ſpoyle of the church, and the deſtruction of Gods people. They who are <hi>Capteines</hi> of two <hi>armies, Pilots</hi> of two <hi>ships, shepherds</hi> of two <hi>flocks, Paſtours</hi> of two <hi>churches</hi> yea and more toe, when a Godlie painfull man, making <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> of his dutye, grones vnder the burden of <hi>one</hi> but they <hi>travailing</hi> at <hi>one</hi> time with <hi>two</hi> children,<note place="margin">Gen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> harder to bring forth then Iacob and Eſau were, cry not out in ſence of any paine, as Rebekah did <hi>ſeing it is ſo why am I thus?</hi> but thinke that their preſence in one place excuſeth their abſence in the other, and the rather, becauſe they ſupply that by their Vicars, or Curates; which in their owne preſence they cannot diſ-charge. But conſider <hi>I beſeech you</hi> as many as be heere <hi>faulty</hi> in this <hi>particular</hi> is your abſence excuſed becauſe by others your places are ſupplyed? what then is the election of miniſters but a ſcorne, and mockerie (as <hi>Dominicus Soto</hi> ſpeaketh writing hereof at large.<note place="margin">Lab. 10.</note>) If a man may take a benefice and diſ-charge it by an other man? and ſeing Chriſt ſendeth you as <hi>Labourers, Teachers,</hi> not ordeiners of <hi>Labourers</hi> and <hi>Teachers</hi> in your places,<note place="margin">De vit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Cap. 22.</note> what is it as <hi>Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſienſis</hi> ſpeaketh writing much to to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, but as if a man should <hi>marry</hi> a woeman vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hope to obteine iſſue of her, but by <hi>another</hi> man?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:17442:15"/>what is it but a croſſe practiſe to that of the <hi>Samaritan,</hi> and of <hi>Christ:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 10.35. Ioh. 21.15 Joh. 19.26</note> of whome, the <hi>former</hi> did not commit the care of the wounded man, to the <hi>Inn-keeper,</hi> till he was to depart himſelfe. The <hi>Lord</hi> did not commit his <hi>sheepe</hi> to <hi>Peter,</hi> nor his <hi>mother</hi> to <hi>Iohn,</hi> till he was now <hi>ready</hi> to commit his ſoule to <hi>God,</hi> and his body to the ground: as <hi>Alphonſus de Castro</hi> diſcourſing hereof at large, ſpeaketh: vnto whome it you be not yet reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved hereof, you may add <hi>Buffus</hi> and <hi>Dumeus de ſacris Eccleſiasticis ministerijs:</hi> but eſpeciallie <hi>Dominicus Soto,</hi> who prooveth this <hi>NON-RE ſidencie</hi> to be vnlawfull by the law of <hi>nature,</hi> by the law of <hi>man,</hi> by the law of <hi>God:</hi> by <hi>Councells</hi> by <hi>Fathers</hi> whome he reckons vp. And, if I did want matter, many more things might heere be <hi>ſpoken</hi> from him: but I onely repeate that ſentence of <hi>Damaſcene</hi> (which he he hath) in an <hi>Epiſtle</hi> of his, which he calleth a <hi>golden Epistle:</hi> where (I take it) he compareth thoſe that leave their <hi>charge</hi> to others, to cruel <hi>harlots,</hi> that ſet forth their children to nurſe, the ſooner, to fulfill their inordinate luſts: So do they ſet forth their <hi>charges</hi> to others, that they may go whither they will the more freely: and intangle themſelves in <hi>ſecular</hi> affaires. <hi>To conclude,</hi> what is it but to ſend <hi>Gehazi</hi> with a <hi>staffe,</hi> that can never recover a dead ſoule to life?</p>
            <p>You, your ſelves muſt put <hi>mouth</hi> to <hi>mouth,</hi> and preach the word vnto them; you muſt put <hi>eyes</hi> to <hi>eyes,</hi> and enlighten their minds; you muſt put <hi>hand</hi> to <hi>hand,</hi> and show them all good examples, in your owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; which if you will not do, but ſtill thinke your <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates</hi> preſence can excuſe your abſence,<note place="margin">Ezek. 44.1.</note> then go to the <hi>Prophet Ezekiel</hi> and put your finger in the <hi>print</hi> of the Prophets ſpeeche that you may not ſtill be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17442:15"/>
but beleeve: that it fully concerneth you: <hi>You have not kept</hi> the ordinances of my holy things ſaith God but you have ſet others to take the charge of my <hi>Sanctuarie. As if he should have ſaide:</hi> you have received the oblation of my holy things: but you have not kept the ordinances of my holy things, and as if you were the <hi>Lords</hi> of my <hi>heritage,</hi> you have put others vnder you, to take the charge of my <hi>Sanctuarie,</hi> which yourſelves should have diſ-charged.</p>
            <p>Thus doeth the Lord plainely reproove you, for <hi>ſubstituting</hi> others vnder you: and therefore may you juſtly feare that which <hi>Claudius Eſpencaus,</hi> a <hi>Papist,</hi> is bold to write, which I am even <hi>a-frayd</hi> to ſpeake: that God shall ſerve you heareafter, as you ſerve him now: you shall be <hi>ſaved</hi> by your <hi>vicars,</hi> but <hi>damned</hi> in your owne <hi>perſons.</hi> And now further, men and bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, if that blind <hi>buzzards</hi> onely which know not the price of ſoules, were <hi>guilty</hi> of this ſinne, I would not have marveiled: or if the purple <hi>Cardinall</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> onely, with that accurſed <hi>rabble</hi> of that <hi>Romish</hi> Court, were guilty of this ſinne, I would have held my peace: but that <hi>learned</hi> men, men of judgment and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, which reade and profeſſe to know the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> and theiſe words pronounced againſt them, no milder then <hi>gall</hi> and <hi>worme-wood;</hi> should be ſo ſore blinded, by that love of the <hi>world</hi> as to ſeeke their owne <hi>eaſe,</hi> their owne <hi>proffit,</hi> their owne <hi>pleaſure:</hi> but not that which is Ieſus Chriſts, not his <hi>glory,</hi> nor the ſalvation of his people. ò ye <hi>heavens</hi> be ashamed at this! &amp; thou ò <hi>earth</hi> conceale not this iniquitie! <hi>Crye</hi> out thou <hi>hunger-starved</hi>-ſoule, as the Soules of the ſlaine, vnder the <hi>altar:</hi> let not your <hi>tongues</hi> cleave to the roofe of your mouth, vntill the Lord, <hi>holy</hi> and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17442:16"/>
               <hi>true,</hi> avenge your blood, on them that ſlay you, as beaſts in the <hi>middeſt</hi> of the <hi>ſtreete!</hi> and thou blood of the ſoule <hi>al-ready</hi> dead: dead in reſpect of any ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual <hi>vegetation,</hi> and dead in everlaſting <hi>malediction,</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be dryed vp, but cry <hi>lowder,</hi> then the blood of Abel againſt Kaine for vengeance, againſt this ſinne! and you that are the <hi>Lords</hi> faithfull <hi>ministers</hi> on earth, regard the ſoules, and ſalvations of Gods people, and let them be as <hi>deare</hi> to you, as they were to him that bought them, with no leſſe <hi>deare</hi> a price, then the price of his owne <hi>blood.</hi> And you <hi>Fathers,</hi> and <hi>brethren,</hi> who in the <hi>miniſterie</hi> live in this <hi>cittie,</hi> and have now long nayled your eares, to the doore-poſts thereof; I ſay not as <hi>Bishop Latymer</hi> ſometime ſaid, to his <hi>fellow-Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops,</hi> let the example of the <hi>Devill</hi> moove you, who is ever diligent, and never <hi>Non-re ſident</hi> in his great <hi>Parish,</hi> but I humbly beſeech you, if there be any place for beſeechig left, let the commandement of Gods word moove you, who willeth you to looke to your <hi>calling,</hi> and abide in that; let the example of Chriſt, and regard to his glory, moove you, who <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe</hi> came to ſeeke the <hi>loſt</hi> sheepe, and finding it, put it vpon his shoulders, and <hi>himſelfe</hi> brought it <hi>home:</hi> let the example of the <hi>Levites,</hi> and all good <hi>over-ſeers</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite you, oh let the <hi>ignorance</hi> of the people, and <hi>dread</hi> to murder their <hi>ſoules</hi> which Chriſt hath purchaſed with his blood, provoke you: yea, let the <hi>care</hi> of your owne <hi>quiet,</hi> and the peace of your owne <hi>conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> which shall heareafter greivouſly rue it, enjoyne you: and let the aſſured <hi>perſuaſion</hi> of Gods goodnes, who hath promiſed to <hi>mainteine</hi> you, and will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it, conſtreine you to redreſſe all <hi>vnfaithfulnrs:</hi> and thinke on thoſe <hi>temptations</hi> which hold you
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17442:16"/>
therein; are they not <hi>groſſe,</hi> and ſuch as the <hi>shame</hi> of the <hi>world</hi> might shift of? how much more should Gods ſpirit prevaile heerevnto! thinke on the <hi>gaine</hi> you get by ſpirituall <hi>promotions,</hi> joyned with ſpirituall <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſtructions,</hi> are they not more shame-full, and infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s, then the <hi>gaines</hi> of the <hi>uſurer</hi> and <hi>promotour?</hi> let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be enough that there be thoſe in <hi>hell</hi> al-ready, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urſe the day that ever you were borne, through whoſe cruelty they are fallen into theiſe vnſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble torments: and from hence forth take heede to your miniſterie and to the faithfull diſ-charge of your duty.</p>
            <p>Let it never be ſaid that you loved the Lord, as <hi>Laban</hi> loved <hi>Iacob,</hi> onely to get riches by him, or as <hi>Saul</hi> loved <hi>David,</hi> to get honour by him, and not for any love to the <hi>perſon</hi> of <hi>Iacob,</hi> or <hi>David;</hi> but let your love be ſeene by your paines in the miniſterie of Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p>Let it never be ſaid, that a good <hi>benefice</hi> is as a <hi>white marke</hi> in a <hi>greene medowe,</hi> ſeene a farr of, and faire to shoote at, but let it be ſaid, that the ſoules and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Gods people, is the thing you aime at. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member this admonition, <hi>take heed to the ministerie,</hi> forget not that of Paul in his <hi>Viſitation Sermon</hi> at Epheſus;<note place="margin">Act. 20.28.29.</note> 
               <hi>Take heed to your ſelves and to all the flock whereof the H. Ghoſt hath made you overſeers to feed the church of God which he hath purchaſed with his owne blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Take heede to the ministerie thou hast received in the Lord. Archippus</hi> did receive his miniſterie in the Lord: that is, of the Lord. Therefore he did not thruſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe into the miniſterie, but had his <hi>calling</hi> of God, and his example is to be marked of all the miniſters of the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17442:17"/>
word:<note place="margin">Doct.</note> 
               <hi>That they have not onely a calling from man but a calling from God:</hi> as all the Prophets of God had: all the Apoſtles of Chriſt had: whoſe <hi>commiſsion</hi> vnto them, was a brazen wall, to ſecure them: and as a <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſe,</hi> and <hi>rocke</hi> to ſtand vpon. If they have a calling from God, they shall ſee a <hi>ſeale</hi> of their miniſterie i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the converſion of ſome ſoules at leaſt; but if t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> have received their miniſterie from man, &amp; not front the Lord,<note place="margin">Ezek. 13.6.</note> they receive a curſe in ſted of a bleſſing, a <hi>woe</hi> is denounced againſt them: and their people con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue without proffit: as God sheweth in the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of Ieremiah: ſaying <hi>I will come against them that Propheſy</hi> falſe <hi>dreames</hi> &amp; <hi>I ſent them not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 23.32.</note> 
               <hi>nor comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therefore</hi> they bring no proffit to this people, ſaith the Lord, <hi>therefore</hi> the people are not bettred, their <hi>ſoules</hi> are not converted, their lives are not amended, <hi>God</hi> is not glorified, becauſe they came, and God <hi>ſent</hi> them not, they had a <hi>ministerie,</hi> but not <hi>of the Lord:</hi> but <hi>ſaith God</hi> in the ſame <hi>chapter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ 22.</note> 
               <hi>if they had stood in my counſel,</hi> and <hi>had declared my word,</hi> to <hi>my people:</hi> then, <hi>they should have turned them from their evill way,</hi> and <hi>from the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes of their inventions. Behold</hi> a bleſſing that should have followed their <hi>labours,</hi> if <hi>God</hi> had ſent them. Reade,<note place="margin">1. Kings. 22. 2 King 3. jer. 6.14. Amos 7. Pſam. 12. Mat 14</note> and conſider, what made <hi>Micajah</hi> ſo <hi>confident</hi> with <hi>Ahab?</hi> what made <hi>Elisha,</hi> a <hi>worme</hi> of the earth, ſo <hi>bold</hi> with <hi>Jehoram?</hi> what made <hi>Ieremie,</hi> ſo plaine with <hi>Preist</hi> and <hi>Prophet?</hi> what made <hi>Amos</hi> ſo <hi>stout</hi> againſt <hi>Amaziah?</hi> what made <hi>Nathan</hi> ſo <hi>free</hi> with <hi>David?</hi> what made <hi>Iohn Baptist</hi> ſo <hi>zealous,</hi> to reproove <hi>Herod?</hi> what did open the <hi>mouthes</hi> of the <hi>Apostles,</hi> and made them ſpeake the <hi>word</hi> with all boldnes of ſpeech, but this warrant of their callinge. They had their <hi>minifierie</hi> not of <hi>man</hi> but of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:17442:17"/>Theiſe are the <hi>faithfull</hi> miniſters of God, whome God hath <hi>called,</hi> and armed from above, to this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
            <p>Theiſe are they, to whome he hath given Crownes of authority, and <hi>lincks</hi> of <hi>iron</hi> to bind the Princes, and nobles of the earth: the reſt have no courage, no power, no zeale at all, whome the Devill feareth not, but eſpying the wants of their <hi>commiſsion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 19.15. <hi>uſe.</hi>
               </note> ſayth to them, as he once did, to the Sonns of Sceva: <hi>Ieſus I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge,</hi> and <hi>Paul I know, but who are yee?</hi> let every <hi>minister</hi> that heareth me this day, enter into his owne <hi>heart,</hi> and examin his inmoſt affection, and <hi>try</hi> whither he hath received his miniſterie of the <hi>Lord,</hi> or no: which he hath not, <hi>unleſſe</hi> he hath <hi>gifts,</hi> in ſome tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable meaſure, to diſ-charge that miniſterie: for <hi>God</hi> ſendeth no <hi>blind guides, unleſſe</hi> it be in <hi>judgment</hi> to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish the <hi>people.</hi> We reade in the booke of <hi>Eſiber,</hi> that none might come into the preſence of the King, <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe</hi> the King did hold out his <hi>golden Scepter</hi> vnto him: how shall they then be punished of the Lord, that come, <hi>not</hi> into Gods <hi>preſence, but</hi> into Gods <hi>place,</hi> where God himſelfe is; even the <hi>Father,</hi> full of <hi>Majeſtie,</hi> the Sonne of God, <hi>replenished</hi> with glory, and the H. Ghoſt great in power: and preſume, to take the place vpon them, without any <hi>warrnt</hi> from the Lord? They are the <hi>vipers</hi> of the <hi>church,</hi> which ſtay not the appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted time of <hi>nature,</hi> but breake out of their <hi>mothers bellyes,</hi> before their time, tho their <hi>mother</hi> pay for it. They will not ſtay, till God openeth them a <hi>doore,</hi> but will run in <hi>another</hi> waye.<note place="margin">what will you give me? what ſhall J give you</note> And <hi>Iudas</hi> with his <hi>quid vos dabitis mihi?</hi> on the one ſide: and Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus with his <hi>quid ego tihi dabo?</hi> on the other ſide: make wicked <hi>bargaines</hi> together; and without any calling
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:17442:18"/>
from God, enter into the <hi>charge</hi> of Gods people. But let them looke, that they who ſet them a-worke, pay them their wages.</p>
            <p>As many as have their miniſterie of the Lord, can ſay as <hi>Paul</hi> did, when the Goſpell was committed vnto him, <hi>you know of the grace which was given vnto me:</hi> but for the reſt, we ſee the miniſterie in them, but we know no grace in them, neither in their <hi>word,</hi> nor <hi>worke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVhich thou hast received of the Lord, or in the Lord.</hi> Hence we learne <hi>againe. That the Lord is the author of the ministerie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Doct. 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It was he that ſent forth <hi>Prophets,</hi> and <hi>Apostles,</hi> and <hi>Evangelists,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.11.12.13.</note> as <hi>extraordinary,</hi> and for a time: and it is he which ſends forth ſtill both <hi>Pastours,</hi> and <hi>teachers,</hi> which be ordinarie, and forever, as Paul sheweth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. cor. 4.1. 2. cor. 5.20</note>And <hi>therefore</hi> are they called <hi>ſervants,</hi> and <hi>ministers</hi> of Chriſt, and Ambaſſadours for Chriſt: to whome, not <hi>man,</hi> but God, did commit the <hi>ministerie</hi> of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">uſe. </seg>1</label> Heere then is <hi>excellent</hi> matter for miniſter and people. For <hi>minister,</hi> he hath received his miniſterie of the Lord: and therefore he muſt give account of his miniſterie, to the Lord.</p>
            <p>Take heed (ſaith Paul to the <hi>Elders</hi> of Epheſus) to your ſelves, and to the <hi>flocke</hi> whereof the <hi>H. Ghost</hi> hath made you <hi>Overſeers:</hi> not <hi>man,</hi> but the <hi>H. Ghoſt</hi> to whome you shall be <hi>accounteable</hi> for all the flocke and therefore take heede to the charge.</p>
            <p>This should be as a <hi>thowſand</hi> Spurrs to our ſides to moove vs to the performance of our dutyes, when we conſider the <hi>Majestie</hi> of <hi>him,</hi> who hath commited the <hi>ministerie</hi> vnto vs: when we conſider, the price of <hi>ſoules,</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:17442:18"/>
that depend vpon vs: when we thinke on that <hi>account.</hi> which we, one day muſt make: when <hi>Peter</hi> shall come before <hi>God,</hi> with his converted Iewes: and <hi>Paul</hi> with his <hi>Gentills; Andrew</hi> with <hi>Achaja; John</hi> with <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iaz Thomas</hi> with <hi>India.</hi> Whome shall we bring with vs? what <hi>ſoules</hi> shall we preſent to God as our <hi>Crowne,</hi> and our <hi>glory?</hi> where shall we find the <hi>ſeale</hi> of our miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie? or, if we have none, by reaſon of our <hi>negligence</hi> and <hi>ignorance;</hi> how shall we dare, to appeare before the Lord, the fearfull judge, of quicke and dead; when he shall ſay; <hi>come give an accounte of thy ſteward-ship.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly;</hi> the <hi>miniſterie</hi> should hence learne, this <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">uſe. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>leſſon</hi> of <hi>inſtruction:</hi> that becauſe the Lord is the <hi>authour</hi> of this miniſterie; <hi>therefore</hi> they muſt in their <hi>miniſterie,</hi> ſeeke the Lords honour; and not their owne: they muſt ſeeke to <hi>enlarge</hi> Gods <hi>church,</hi> and not their owne livings; to winn <hi>glory</hi> to God, and not <hi>gaine</hi> to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: for, <hi>they</hi> have received their miniſterie in the Lord; by his <hi>grace,</hi> and for his <hi>glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A juſt <hi>reproofe,</hi> to thoſe, who in the <hi>miniſterie</hi> aime not at this <hi>end;</hi> nay, whoſe <hi>conſciences</hi> tell them, they thought not therevpon; but on their owne eaſe, ſuch, and ſuch a benefice, ſuch a <hi>prebend-ship,</hi> ſuch a <hi>common,</hi> ſuch a <hi>Bishoprick,</hi> ſuch <hi>credit,</hi> &amp; <hi>countenance</hi> in the <hi>world:</hi> &amp; intend this end in their <hi>ministerie,</hi> &amp; not the other.</p>
            <p>A juſt <hi>reproofe</hi> of thoſe, who <hi>preach</hi> themſelves, &amp; not the <hi>Lord:</hi> ſpeaking to the eare, &amp; not to the <hi>conſcience:</hi> ſeeking, rather by a <hi>painted eloquence,</hi> to ſet forth them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, &amp; to get the name of <hi>Schollers,</hi> and <hi>learned</hi> men; then to ſet forth the <hi>knowledge</hi> of the trueth: being like to <hi>adulterers,</hi> (as <hi>Gregorie</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pareth them) who delight in the company of <hi>woemen,</hi> not ſo much to get <hi>children,</hi> as to ſatisfy their owne <hi>beaſtly</hi> luſts: <hi>So</hi> do theiſe, delight
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17442:19"/>
to <hi>preach,</hi> now and then; once a <hi>moneth</hi> once a-<hi>quarter,</hi> or <hi>ſo:</hi> but not ſo much to gett <hi>children</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> as to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy, their owne vainglorious humour: as he, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth into the <hi>feild,</hi> to fight with a <hi>poſie</hi> of flowres, in ſtead of a <hi>ſword:</hi> &amp; a <hi>plame</hi> of <hi>fethers</hi> in ſtead of a <hi>buckler:</hi> commeth more like a <hi>Carpet-knight,</hi> then a man of <hi>armes:</hi> ſo may we rightly <hi>judge</hi> him, that commeth into Gods place, with curious <hi>phraſes,</hi> and invented <hi>words,</hi> of mans <hi>wiſdome,</hi> thereby to get <hi>applauſe</hi> of the ſimple: rather like a <hi>wanton man-pleaſer</hi> then a <hi>faithfull Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">uſe. </seg>3</label> Thirdly; let all faithfull <hi>ministers,</hi> comfort themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves herein; tho <hi>men</hi> be againſt them, yet, they have their <hi>calling,</hi> from the Lord: <hi>he</hi> will backe them, and <hi>beare</hi> them out: he will give <hi>power</hi> vnto them. They are <hi>ſtarrs</hi> in Gods right hand; God will <hi>defend</hi> them. Feare not therefore, the <hi>faces</hi> of men; ſeeke not to pleaſe men,<note place="margin">Gal. 1.10.</note> for, if you doe, (as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes) you cannot be the <hi>ſervants</hi> of God. You have your <hi>mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie</hi> from the Lord, ſeeke therefore, to <hi>approove</hi> your ſelves, not to the <hi>wicked,</hi> but to the <hi>Lord,</hi> who will <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel. 11.3.4.5.6.7</note> and give <hi>power</hi> vnto you, as he <hi>promiſeth,</hi> to his two <hi>witneſſes,</hi> in the <hi>Revelation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, for the people: here is alſo a <hi>leſſon</hi> for them to learne: the <hi>Lord</hi> is the <hi>authour</hi> of the <hi>ministerie,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>honourable</hi> is their <hi>calling,</hi> &amp; they are to be had, in ſingular <hi>accounte,</hi> for their <hi>works</hi> ſake: not, for their <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings</hi> ſake, nor <hi>degrees</hi> ſake, nor, their <hi>perſons</hi> ſake, nor, their <hi>freinds</hi> ſake: but, for their <hi>works</hi> ſake. The <hi>worke</hi> of their <hi>calling,</hi> their honourable <hi>calling.</hi> For this <hi>cauſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the <hi>minister</hi> is <hi>called,</hi> the <hi>man</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> as if he should ſay, Gods <hi>Embaſſadour</hi> and <hi>legate,</hi> and <hi>lieutenant,</hi> on <hi>earth.</hi> If then, it be an <hi>honourable</hi> thing, to be a <hi>Princes Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour;</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:17442:19"/>
how much more, to be Gods Embaſſadour,<note place="margin">Revel. 3. revel. 12.4</note> 
               <hi>King</hi> of heaven, and earth? Therefore, called <hi>Angells,</hi> and <hi>Starrs,</hi> to shew, the <hi>excellencie</hi> of their <hi>calling:</hi> which <hi>Paul</hi> conſidering, he cryes out in a <hi>wonder: how beautifull are the feete,</hi> that is, the comming of them,<note place="margin">rom. 10.15</note> 
               <hi>which bring glad tidings of peace?</hi> As if, he should have ſaid, I cannot expreſſe, how <hi>beautifuil,</hi> and <hi>excellent,</hi> how lovely, and amiable, their <hi>comming</hi> is. <hi>See</hi> what <hi>accounte, Elizeus</hi> made of, <hi>Elias;</hi> who being taken vp, <hi>Elizeus</hi> looketh after him, and cryeth out: <hi>Oh the Charriots of Iſrael &amp; the horſmen thereof!</hi> ſignifying, that Elias being gone,<note place="margin">2 King. 2.12.</note> the very beauty, and ſtrength of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> was gone.</p>
            <p>If this were well <hi>regarded,</hi> then the <hi>miniſterie</hi> of God, would be more regarded, <hi>leſſe</hi> deſpiſed, <hi>leſſe</hi> diſ-gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, <hi>more</hi> honoured, <hi>more</hi> reverenced, <hi>more</hi> eſteemed then it is: but for want of this <hi>conſideration,</hi> the <hi>miniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> of <hi>God</hi> are accounted now a dayes, as the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> were before them;<note place="margin">1 cor 4.13</note> the very <hi>filth</hi> and <hi>off-ſkouring</hi> of the world: the very <hi>off alls,</hi> and refuſe, of <hi>mankind.</hi> And, if by our dishonouring God, in our places, and our <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull</hi> walking, in our <hi>calling,</hi> God hath juſtly disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured vs, and made vs <hi>baſe,</hi> and <hi>vile; abject,</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible,</hi> in the ſight of the people; let vs blame our ſelves: but if any, doe eſteeme thus, of Gods <hi>miniſterie,</hi> and account, the calling of his miniſters, dishonoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; they dishonour, not vs, but God, whoſe meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and Embaſſadours, we are: as God ſaid to Moſes:<note place="margin">Num. 14 17. 1. ſam. 8.7</note> 
               <hi>they have not murmured againſt thee, but me:</hi> and, <hi>ſo</hi> he ſaid to <hi>Samuel: they have not rejected thee, but they have caſt me away, from being King over them.</hi> Let them remember, that fearefull ſpeech; <hi>he that deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me. Chriſt,</hi> shall take that dishonour, done to his miniſter, as done to himſelfe. And therefore, if <hi>David</hi> would
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:17442:20"/>
not put vp that diſ-grace which was offred to his <hi>meſſengers</hi> by <hi>Hanun:</hi> certeynely, <hi>Chriſt</hi> will not put vp that <hi>diſ-grace,</hi> which is offred, to his <hi>meſſengers,</hi> and <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</hi> Wherefore, I heere <hi>dare,</hi> all <hi>Papiſts, Atheiſts, Libertines, Newters, Machiavells,</hi> and, all prophane <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures</hi> whoſoever, to contemne the miniſters of God: if thou <hi>dareſt</hi> dishonour them, diſ-grace them, mocke them, and laugh at them: <hi>Call</hi> them, <hi>peſtilent</hi> fellowes, as <hi>Tertullus</hi> did: and <hi>troublers</hi> of the <hi>ſtate,</hi> as <hi>Ahab</hi> did <hi>Elias,</hi> a troubler of <hi>Iſrael: Call</hi> them <hi>mad-fellowes,</hi> as <hi>Eraſtus</hi> did,<note place="margin">Act.</note> in his mad <hi>moode: Call</hi> them, <hi>railing</hi> prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, <hi>ſeditous</hi> preachers: aſſure they ſelfe, who ever thou art, that; thus <hi>thinkeſt</hi> in thy heart: or, <hi>ſpeakeſt</hi> with thy mouth: the <hi>Lord,</hi> of whome, we have received our miniſterie, shall not forget this contempt: but, tho baſe be our <hi>perſons,</hi> poore be our <hi>livings,</hi> disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable be our <hi>eſtimation:</hi> he shall remember, and he shall revenge it. And therefore, feare to vilify, any of thoſe, who have their miniſtery from the Lord. <hi>Men</hi> we are, as you are: and that is for your good, for you could not heare the voice, of God himſelfe, and live: or, of any of thoſe <hi>bleſſed;</hi> and <hi>glorious Angels</hi> of his. <hi>Sinfull</hi> we are, as yee are: and that is, becauſe we are men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mortall</hi> we are, as you are: and that is, becauſe we are ſinfull. Yet ſtill, tho <hi>men, ſinfull,</hi> and <hi>mortall,</hi> we are the <hi>meſſengers</hi> of God, and <hi>Ambaſſadours</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> If you love vs not, in regard of our <hi>perſons,</hi> yet love vs, in regard of our <hi>office:</hi> we are indeed, but earthen veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells; but we have <hi>pretious</hi> treaſures in vs: if, you eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me vs not, becauſe we are <hi>veſſells,</hi> and of <hi>earth,</hi> yet honour vs, for the <hi>treaſures</hi> ſake. Our miniſterie is not ours, but the Lords, <hi>we,</hi> and thrice <hi>wee</hi> be to him,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17442:20"/>
that <hi>ſcorueth</hi> it.</p>
            <p>The laſt thing, comes to be conſidered,<note place="margin">Doct. 5.</note> in this verſe. <hi>That thou fulfil it.</hi> It is heere <hi>required</hi> of the <hi>minister,</hi> that, he thinke it not enough, to diſ-charge his duty, <hi>coldly,</hi> and <hi>perfunctorily,</hi> and for fashion (as it were) but, he muſt ſett himſelfe to it, <hi>earneſtly, zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly,</hi> and <hi>fervently,</hi> that he may even <hi>fulfill</hi> it: that he may, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>make his ministery fully knowne:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.</note> and, approove himſelfe, the true <hi>minister</hi> of <hi>Christ:</hi> and make it appeare, by all meanes, that it is his <hi>hearts</hi> deſire, to fulfill his <hi>ministery:</hi> So did <hi>Apollos,</hi> preaching <hi>fervently,</hi> &amp; teaching diligently, the things of the <hi>Lord.</hi> Firſt, he ſpake <hi>fervently,</hi> and then taught: noting thereby, that many ſpeake, who do not teach, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſpeake not <hi>fervently,</hi> as <hi>Apollos.</hi> Thus did <hi>Paul,</hi> burne in Spirit, and then, he teſtified to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> that <hi>Ieſus</hi> was the Lord. Thus did <hi>Chriſt</hi> preach:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oh. 7.</note> of whome, the <hi>Phariſes meſſengers,</hi> gave this teſtimony, and <hi>ingenuouſly</hi> confeſſed; <hi>never man ſpake like this man:</hi> becauſe, he ſpake <hi>zealouſly,</hi> and with authority, and,<note place="margin">mat. 7.</note> not <hi>coldly,</hi> and <hi>faintly</hi> as did the Scribes.</p>
            <p>Tho a man, had all knowledg, of all <hi>Fathers, ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues</hi> and <hi>arts,</hi> yet <hi>unleſſe</hi> he have zeale,<note place="margin">Act. 2.</note> he can never <hi>fulfill,</hi> the miniſtery of Chriſt. Therefore, did the H. Ghoſt deſcend, in the likenes of cloven tongues, like fire; to ſignify a zealous, a hott, preaching miniſterie. Iohn was a <hi>burning,</hi> as well as a <hi>shining</hi> light:<note place="margin">ioh.</note> So muſt we burne with zeale, if we will fulfill the miniſterie.</p>
            <p>If this be ſo, what shall we ſay, of theiſe cold, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortles <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">uſe. </seg>1</label> diſcourſes, and <hi>morrall-philoſophy</hi>-lectures, (rather then Sermons) without zeale, of <hi>formall</hi>-preaching miniſters, which shame the heate, by which men should be quickened; being as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeakes
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17442:21"/>
               <hi>luciferi,</hi> but, not <hi>igniferi,</hi> having, ſome light of <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> in their <hi>heads,</hi> but, no fire of <hi>zeale,</hi> in their <hi>hearts,</hi> who, ſpeaking the word of God, do weaken the power thereof, by <hi>dulnes,</hi> and <hi>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nes</hi> of Spirit; bringing forth their doctrines, as many woemen do their children; <hi>still-borne,</hi> without ſence, without feeling, without motion; uſing <hi>doctrine,</hi> without <hi>application; application,</hi> without <hi>zeale,</hi> like men without ſoules, or <hi>Images</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out lives. Such were, the intollerable cold, <hi>collations,</hi> of the <hi>Scribes,</hi> and <hi>Phariſes,</hi> whereby, they did looſe their Auditours, and, made their <hi>Synagogues,</hi> deſolate: and ſuch are the <hi>Sermons,</hi> of thoſe miniſters, whoſe <hi>minds</hi> are drowned, in wordly matters, whoſe <hi>ſpirits</hi> are frozen, and pittifully benummed, with <hi>woldlines,</hi> and <hi>ſenſuality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, ſo <hi>dull</hi> are their owne hearts, by want of holy <hi>meditation,</hi> that, they have no life, in their <hi>ministerie,</hi> nor power in their <hi>preaching,</hi> more, then when, a little boy,<note place="margin">2. tim. 1.6.</note> ſaith grace. Wherefore, as <hi>Paul</hi> bids <hi>Timothy, to stirr up,</hi>
               <note place="margin">anadſopu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</note> 
               <hi>the graces of God in him;</hi> to blow them, as it were with <hi>bellowes,</hi> as, the <hi>Greeke</hi> word, imports: ſo muſt we, and <hi>endevour,</hi> to <hi>Godly</hi> vehemency; in our preaching, that, we may enforce our doctrine, to the hearts of the hearers, and, may make our miniſterie, <hi>knowne</hi> to Gods <hi>people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>lastly;</hi> that our <hi>ministerie,</hi> may be fulfilled; let vs be,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.12.</note> to them that <hi>beleeve,</hi> as <hi>Enſamples,</hi> in <hi>word,</hi> in <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation,</hi> in <hi>love,</hi> in <hi>ſpirit,</hi> &amp; in <hi>purenes,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh to <hi>Timothy:</hi> let vs labour, to be <hi>unreprooveable,</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out blame, that, we ſett an edge, on our <hi>Sermons,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> may, by our owne life, <hi>authorice</hi> our doctrine; let us <hi>first,</hi> be <hi>confirmed,</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> was, and ſtrengthen others; let vs <hi>first,</hi> obſerve the <hi>commandements</hi> of God, &amp; then
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17442:21"/>
teach them others to obſerve; let vs <hi>first, labour</hi> to be the <hi>ſervants</hi> of God, as <hi>Paul</hi> was, and then, the <hi>Apostles</hi> of Ieſus Chriſt; let vs have in our <hi>brest-plate,</hi> both <hi>urim,</hi> and <hi>Thummim,</hi> both knowledg, and holines, and, in the outmoſt <hi>borders,</hi> of our <hi>garments,</hi> let there be, both, <hi>bells,</hi> and <hi>pomegranates</hi> toe, both, <hi>ſoundnes</hi> of doctrine, and <hi>ſweetnes</hi> of converſation. Take away the <hi>reproch</hi> of the people, that hath, a great while taken vp,<note place="margin">rom. 2.</note> that ſpeech; <hi>Thou that teachest another, teachest thou not thy ſelfe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You are in the face of the people, a <hi>fault</hi> in you, is, as a <hi>staine</hi> in the face, and a <hi>blow</hi> in the eye: as moſt perſpicuous, ſo moſt dangerous, in the <hi>hand,</hi> the <hi>glove</hi> may cover it: in the <hi>feete,</hi> the <hi>shooes</hi> may cover it: in the <hi>body,</hi> the <hi>clothes</hi> may cover it: in a <hi>child,</hi> his <hi>age:</hi> in a <hi>woe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> her <hi>ſexe:</hi> in a <hi>private</hi> man, his <hi>ignorance</hi> may <hi>excuſe</hi> it: in you, that muſt be <hi>Enſamples</hi> to others, in all kind of converſation, nothing can excuſe it. <hi>Therefore,</hi> if there be heere, any <hi>lizards,</hi> that, do wipe out with their <hi>tayle,</hi> the print of their feete, made in the duſt: any <hi>preacher,</hi> who, by the <hi>uncleane</hi> tayle, of a looſe life, wipes out the <hi>print,</hi> of true doctrine; if any have <hi>Iacobs</hi> voyce, and <hi>Eſaws</hi> hands, if any, that carry the <hi>bellowes</hi> of preaching in the <hi>one</hi> hand, to kindle, and the water of <hi>ungodlines,</hi> in the other, to quench it: let them not deceive themſelves, by their preaching, their <hi>ministery,</hi> is not fulfilled, and therefore, they shall have their <hi>portion,</hi> with that ſervant, that knowes his <hi>maſters</hi> will, and doeth it not.</p>
            <p>And now to <hi>Conclude</hi> all, I ſay vnto all <hi>take heed to your miniſterie:</hi> for the <hi>devill</hi> your <hi>adverſary,</hi> [there is his dread] as a <hi>lyon,</hi> [there is his power] as a <hi>rouring lyon</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:17442:22"/>
[there is his deſire to hurt] <hi>goeth about,</hi> [there is his induſtrie] and <hi>ſeeketh</hi> [there is more then ordinary di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, not <hi>what,</hi> but, <hi>whome,</hi> he may devoure: Even the ſoules of men, that is his <hi>preye.</hi> His <hi>force,</hi> very greate, his <hi>wiles,</hi> and <hi>advantages,</hi> not unowne, his <hi>malice</hi> experienced, his <hi>cruelty,</hi> ſuch as as <hi>hell</hi> can afforde; therefore, <hi>take heede to your miniſterie.</hi> The wicked, your enimies, are <hi>Eagle-eyld,</hi> to looke into you, and ſpye you, as narrowly, as the Romans did <hi>Cato,</hi> or the <hi>Phariſes, Chriſt;</hi> to find a fault, and having found, either your <hi>ignorance,</hi> or, your negligence, or, the <hi>pride</hi> of your <hi>ambition,</hi> or, your <hi>covetouſnes,</hi> they have enough, to talke of, with joy on every ale-bench. <hi>Others</hi> ſee your faults, and <hi>weepe,</hi> in ſecret, for your ſinns, that Gods glorious goſpel, that ſweete oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, should be carried in ſuch filthy <hi>boxes,</hi> as ſome of you are. <hi>Take heede to your miniſterie you have received in the Lord:</hi> you have received <hi>of</hi> the <hi>Lord:</hi> to him, you muſt give <hi>account,</hi> you have received it for the <hi>Lord,</hi> to him you muſt performe your dutye, shame not him, that hath called you, walke <hi>worthy</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> approove your ſelves, as <hi>workmen,</hi> that need not, to be <hi>ashamed,</hi> in fulfilling this your <hi>miniſterie:</hi> for, if you have bene faithfull, there is layd vp for you, a <hi>Crowne</hi> of glorye, which, God, the righteous <hi>judge,</hi> shall give you at that day: if <hi>unfaithfull,</hi> go many <hi>fathomes,</hi> deeper into <hi>hell,</hi> then other men, becauſe you have bene, the <hi>Soule-murderers</hi> of them, whome you should have ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Thus, as the <hi>Coloſsians</hi> muſt ſay to <hi>Archippus,</hi> ſo I to you, every one, <hi>take heede to your miniſterie, which you have received in the Lord that you fulfill it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Even ſo good Lord, grant vnto the <hi>miniſterie,</hi> of thy choſen ones all gifts, fit for their calling, give vnto
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17442:22"/>
them, increaſe of knowledge, give them <hi>faithfulnes</hi> give them <hi>zeale,</hi> that they may teach thy people, in thy trueth!</p>
            <p>And <hi>reforme,</hi> all them; that either, for <hi>ignorance</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not: or, for <hi>negligence,</hi> will not; or, for <hi>fearfulnes,</hi> dare not; or, for <hi>wickednes,</hi> and <hi>ungodlines,</hi> ought not, to preach thy word: that true <hi>Paſtours,</hi> being pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in, among thy people, which may feed them, with knowledg, and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, thy <hi>church</hi> may grow vp, in perfect beauty, to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of thy name! <hi>Amen!</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17442:23"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17442:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:17442:24"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:17442:24"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:17442:25"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:17442:25"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:17442:26"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:17442:26"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:17442:27"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:17442:27"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:17442:28"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:17442:28"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:17442:29"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:17442:29"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:17442:30"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:17442:30"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:17442:31"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:17442:31"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:17442:32"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:17442:32"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
